Today's daf is נ"א, nun aleph, 51. And we pick up middle
of נ' עמוד ב', nun amud bet, so we have a little
catching up to do. And the discussion here is in the middle
of all these תיקון עולםs tikkun olam in terms of collecting of
debts. And the גמרא Gemara wants to know that the one תיקון
עולם tikkun olam is that
creditors cannot collect property that has liens on it that's held by
third parties if the debtor, original debtor, still has available assets,
בני חורין. bnei chorin. You can't collect from משועבדים meshubadim במקום שיש
בני חורין. bimkom sheyesh bnei chorin. And presumably that means even if
the
greater property that they're entitled to, grade B, is in the hands
of the third party and they only have grade C in the
hands of the original debtor, they have to collect what the debtor
has before they can go to a third party. So the question
raised in the גמרא Gemara is, well, this clearly you understand why
we would have to institute this to protect people who buy land.
They don't want everybody to go straight to the land they bought.
They want them to be the sort of, what's it called, the
option of last resort. Anyway, whatever. Resort, they want them to be
the option of last resort. They want to be protected. But would
it apply even in a case where somebody was given a gift
of land, that the creditor could not go to them if they
could still collect from the original debtor? So the גמרא, Gemara, to
prove this, brings the case of a ברייתא braita that has a
person on his deathbed distributing his property, 200, 300, and 400 to
different people. And if he didn't use the word אחריו, acharav, then
we assume that there's no specific order there and they divide, even
if there's less than 900, they divide equally into nine portions, each
one getting a proportional amount. If he said אחריו, acharav, though, however,
and then if there's less, it's, you know, whatever less is, it's
everybody gets a proportional less. If, however, he said אחריו, acharav, then
you first give the full amount to number one, then anything left
to number two, and anything left to number three. Okay. And the
relevance of this, and let's read the last line of this ברייתא
braita to get us into why this is relevant for us. But
the basic thing to acknowledge here is that right away we're talking
about a gift, he's gifting this property. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says in the middle of נ' עמוד ב', nun amud bet,
let's, we might as well take it from the beginning of the
ברייתא, braita, about 10 lines from the top, תא שמע. tashma. שכיב
מרע sh'chiv meira שאומר תנו מאתים זוז לפלוני וג' מאות לפלוני וארבע
מאות לפלוני, she'omer tnu matayim zuz l'ploni v'gimal me'ot l'ploni v'arba me'ot
l'ploni, אין אומרים כל הקודם בשטר זכה. ein amrim kol hakodam bashtar
zachah. You don't say that the first guy who was given 200,
he has first rights if there's less than the full amount. You
don't since he didn't use the word אחריו acharav and he assigned
to all three people, it's all divided equally. לפיכך יצא עליו שטר
חוב, lefikach yatzah alav shtar chov, if there's a creditor and he
has to, so they've divided the property. Maybe there was exactly 900.
Maybe there was 450, whatever it was. And then it turns out
that actually the estate owed some money. So and this is the
only place that there's money from. Obviously those debts have to be
paid off before these gifts can be given. I mean in that
person anyway, you know, it's not given, he had liens, it wouldn't
be any different if the guy gave the gift in his life.
That creditor had liens and so on. So you pay off the
creditor and with the remaining money you divide what's left between these
three people. Okay. גובה מכולם, goveh mikulam, it's taken equally or proportionally
from all of them.
He has the option, he can go to any of the, he
could go to all, equally, equally. Like it doesn't matter who he
collects from, he collects from one and then they repool and redistribute
the property. Okay. Yes, thank you for that clarification. Okay. So that's
if they all sort of are given it equally. Now, אבל אם
אמר תנו מאתים זוז לפלוני ואחריו לפלוני ואחריו לפלוני, aval im amar
tnu matayim zuz l'ploni v'acharav l'ploni v'acharav l'ploni, if he gave a
sequence, in that case, okay, אומרים כל הקודם בשטר זכה, omrin kol
hakodam bashtar zachah, the first person, if there's a limited estate, he's
given his full amount and only then you move on to number
two and only then you move on to number three. לפיכך יצא
עליו שטר חוב, lefikach yatzah alav shtar chov, so you divided it
all up. There was enough for all three of those guys. Let's
say. Okay. You divided it all up. But then there's a creditor.
So he has liens on the property. He has to be paid
off. He's paid off. And now there's not a sufficient amount to
be divided by those three. So in that case, יצא עליו שטר
חוב, yatzah alav shtar chov, גובה מן האחרון, gove minei ha'acharon, so
he collects from the last guy. He goes to guy number three
because guy number three is the, you know, last, whatever, last in,
first out or whatever. You know, he's the guy that's going to
lose out. He's the guy who gets less. אין לו, ein lo,
if the last guy is not enough for to pay off the
debt, גובה משלפניו, gove mishilifanav, he goes to guy number two. אין
לו, ein lo, if there's not enough, גובה משלפניו, gove mishilifanav, you
go to number one. That's the ברייתא. braita. Okay. All that makes
a lot of sense. But here's the גמרא's Gemara question of why
it's relevant. Okay. The גמרא Gemara says like this, one minute,
ואף על גב דקמא בינונית ובתרא זיבורית מזבורית גבי מבינונית לא גבי.
v'af al gav d'kama beinonit u'basra ziborit, m'ziborit gavi, m'beinonit lo gavi.
So basically, let's imagine the scenario. The ברייתא braita doesn't distinguish between
the grade of property. So presumably we're talking that even if the
third guy was given grade C, right? And the first guy was
given grade B. Okay, which anyway presumably the first guy would want
the better property, he's the one that has first rights and so
on. Okay, so you get it, the first guy got grade B
and then you gave to the other guy, third guy gets grade
C, creditor comes with his שטר חוב, shtar chov, I'm owed 200
bucks, okay, we tell him well you gotta go to guy number
three cause he was the last guy in the line. Okay, but
why doesn't he say wait a minute, that was a, or all
these guys got as a by virtue of a מתנה, matana, מתנה
matana is not right? The reason guy number three, he has to
collect from guy number three is, you know, you basically right if
you have like guy number one, guy number two, guy number three,
they got they got all their properties, and he got grade C
and he got let's say he got grade B, okay? So basically
this guy's debt, this was when it was it was all gifted,
when the guy was on his deathbed, okay? This guy's debt pre-existed.
The debt was prior to this time, okay? And he had liens
on the grade B property, right? Yes, right? He had liens on
the grade B property. What? Okay, so therefore then it was gifted.
So this grade B property was given to guy number one. Well,
he should say, and but after it was given to guy number
one the estate still had you know let's call both of these
C, the estate still had two Cs left. Okay, if he were
to come and have collected at this moment before it was given
to these guys number two and three, okay? You with me? Everybody,
right? What what would we have said? We would have said, well
you gotta go to C, right? Cause cause he still has C
left. Says no, I'm not going to C, I'm entitled to B,
I'm collecting from guy number one, right? So therefore that's, he's entitled,
his liens are on this. So why do we force him to
go to guy number three? He should say it's all very nice,
you've got this whole order of your gifting and you want guy
number three to lose out. I want the land of B that
I'm entitled to. Okay? So so the fact that we don't let
him do this and we basically say no, once that was given
away you're left to collecting from here, shows that even in a
case of a gift we protect the receiver of the gift. And
therefore once that was given away he's left with those two things.
Okay? You got it? And therefore as it continues to be given
away he has to collect from the very last one. That's that's
that's why it's a proof for our case.
If, if, after he he became indebted to this other fellow. Right.
Why
should that other fellow who he became indebted to be neglected in
that way?
Well that's exactly the point. So that's the הלכה halacha which is
is that if you once if you sell your property and here
we're including it if you give away your property then the debtor
doesn't can't go to those people they're they're forced to collect from
what's left over.
I know I'm just saying why.
Yeah well we're trying to protect these people, we're trying to protect
people from collecting from buying land that they don't have to risk
always losing the land that they bought. And here we're applying it
even to a מתנה. matana. But your point is, but that comes
at the expense of the people that are loaning money. I understand,
you know, that's that's the way things are usually in business. Something
that protects one party usually winds up hurting another party. Yeah I
mean you're right. Yes.
But couldn't they first like investigate to find out if there's a
lien on this property?
Yeah I mean no I understand but the point is is that
yeah but the point is is that if I know when I
buy property, if I know if I know that the debtor can
come straight to me without first trying to collect from this guy,
like it's gonna the concern is it's gonna put a huge damp
on the market, you know? But I it's yeah there's a trade-off.
Yeah.
This הלכה halacha applies only where they שבו מה שאמרו? shvu ma
she-amru?
Yeah, exactly. Okay so now the גמרא gemara says,
where are we? ואף אגב דקיימא בינונית ובתרא זיבורית, Va-af agav de-kaima
beinonis u-basra ziboris, wait a minute, ואף אגב דקיימא בינונית ובתרא זיבורית,
Va-af agav de-kaima beinonis u-basra ziboris, מזיבורית גבי
מבינונית לא גבי. mi-ziboris gavi, mi-beinonis lo gavi. שמע מינה במתנה נמי
Shema mina be-matana nami even when it's a gift, you know, he
lose his the credit the creditor loses out. So the גמרא gemara
says not necessarily. הכא במאי עסקינן Hacha be-mai askinan בבעל חוב be-ba'al
chov that these people actually when it says that the money is
distributed to them it wasn't gifted to them, the guy on his
deathbed was saying pay these guys off, I owe them this money.
Okay so therefore that's why they're protected because they're being paid off,
of course that's a very and it's not just a gift, of
course that's not at all the פשט. pshat. So the גמרא gemara
says ולחזי שטרא דמאן קדים, Ve-lachzei shtara de-man kadim, one minute, if
they're being paid off, נו, nu, did I skip a line?
בבעל חוב. Be-ba'al chov. והא תנו קאמר, Ve-ha tnu ka'amar, one minute,
he says give it to A, B, and C. No, תנו בחובו,
Tnu be-chovo, I mean pay me off my debts. So the גמרא
gemara says then why do we give it in a particular order?
If they're being creditors paid off by their
debt. that's earlier dated, וליכא שטרא, v'leika shtar, they don't have a
document, which explains why this guy has prior rights because they don't
have any proof that they're owed the money, okay, you got it?
He's paying off, right, he, the guy on his deathbed is admitting
he owes the money to these guys, they don't have any proof,
so they don't know which order to collect, he's admitting he owes
the money, this guy has a document that has proof, that has
earlier liens, so he's entitled to seize from them, okay, but because
they're being paid off on a debt, they're protected, okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says, והא כל הקודם בשטר קאמר, v'ha kol hakodem bishtar
ka'amar, but then it says that
it serves one, two, and three, whoever was earlier in the document
has more rights, so that sounds like the way you're reading it
that it's a debt, it means the document of debt, גמרא Gemara
says no, בשטר פקדתא, bishtar pekadata, no, no, no, we mean the
deathbed-like document that he basically said give to one, two, and three,
so whichever was earlier in that document means in that declaration, you
know, gets more rights, okay, so basically how did we explain that
it looks here like these people who received a gift are protected,
you know, this guy's protected because there was money left over even
if it was a lesser grade, and גמרא Gemara says no, it
wasn't being given as a gift, it was being paid off as
a loan, okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, yeah,
so I still am not clear,
why isn't the debt and נפסד nifsad had had being paid back
creditors, yeah, he's a creditor too,
yeah, but that's what I said, they don't have any proof so
their liens are meaningless, so his lien is more, his lien... they're
protected in terms of this תקנה takana that this guy is told
if there's money left over he's got to collect, but they lose
out to him because they don't have any שטר, shtar, they don't
have any evidence of
liens, exactly, he'll collect from them, they just won't be able
to get the...
yeah, exactly, yeah, he's collecting, he's just getting the worst grade,
ושמואל אמר v'shmuel amar had said like, you know, you have to
pay
first one, two, and three because their liens are first, even though
there's no
document, בזמן דחב לאחרים, bazman d'chav l'acherim, we wouldn't believe him, okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
okay, ואיבעית אימא, ve'ibayis eima, אפילו מתנה נמי, afilu matana nami, let's
go back to the פשט, pshat, it's a gift, ולא קשיא, v'lo
kashya, מה גובה מן האחרון, mah goveh min ha'acharon, אין נפסד אלא
האחרון, ein nifsad ela ha'acharon, the גמרא Gemara says you misunderstood it,
גובה מן האחרון goveh min ha'acharon means this guy once the estate
is taken, you know, has less funds, the last guy loses out,
but it doesn't mean he takes guy number three's property, okay, he
goes ahead and he takes the B property, maybe the person who
received the gift is not protected, and he's going to take the
property that he's entitled to, grade number B, but then you know
what you're going to do? You're going to redistribute it, so when
it says the last guy loses out, it doesn't mean he takes
the last guy's property, he takes the property he's entitled to, you
redistribute it so the last guy winds up losing out, but you
don't start by taking his property, okay, which is a completely reasonable
read, אין נפסד אלא האחרון, ein nifsad ela ha'acharon, okay, the last
guy loses out because he's the last in line, but maybe the
creditor is entitled to his grade B property, ואיבעית אימא דשוו כולהו
להדדי, ve'ibayis eima d'shavu kulahu lahadadi, and the final answer is is
not an interesting one, that that we just happen to be talking
that they all have equal grade, equal grade land, we're not talking
about a case where there's different grade land, so we leave with
that question unresolved, do when they protected the people who bought land
that the creditors have are forced to go to the original, you
know, the principal, the person who who owes them money, even if
that person has lesser grade land, right, did they protect even people
not only who bought land, but even people who received land as
a gift? And we don't know the answer, but as David's question
correctly points out, you know, any תקנה takana here, anything to protect
one party hurts another party, so that's the תיקון עולם tikkun olam
choice that you have to make, right, which is what's more in
society's interest in terms of who to be protecting and at whose
cost, all right, so now the גמרא Gemara continues, אין מוציאין לאכילת
פירות, ein motzi'in la'achilas peiros, so we do not, we do not,
another group of people we're protecting is,
I have a lien on your land, you sell your land, so
here we have these person, you know, so this person, the לוקח
loke'ach who bought your land, I now want my debt paid, I'm
going to go to that land and seize it that's now in
the hand of the third party, what if that debt that's owed
to me is not a known amount when you actually bought the
land, okay, so David, you bought the land here from Michael, Michael
owes me a thousand dollars, okay, okay, so you buy that land,
so you know you're risking... keep on knowing you're only me, thank
you, you know, David, that you when you buy that land from
Michael that a thousand dollars of that land is potentially at risk
because I might come and seize it in my debt, right, but
let's say the amount Michael owes me is... not determined yet, okay?
Then you are... well, we'll go, I'll tell you in a minute.
I already got you worried. You see that? So in that case,
in that case, you're like saying, "Whoa, how can I go ahead
and engage in this transaction and not even know how much is
at risk?" Okay, now what's the case that it's not determined yet?
There are a couple scenarios. I'll start with the early one, which
is the second one in the משנה, Mishna, but it's easier to
describe. Which is that my daughters, who I don't have, my daughters
are entitled after I die to go ahead and be supported by
the estate, okay? As long, you know, until they get married or
whatever. Now, that could be years, and I could have another five
daughters, you know, between now and whatever they get whatever. So you
have no idea, and that... they have liens on that estate. If
they can go ahead and not just collect, you know, you know,
collect... so I'm now the person, I guess I'm now in Michael's
side. I'm now the person that, meaning, my daughters are now the
creditors. They're the ones money is owed to, right? So and they
have a right to collect from that estate, but it's in no
way determined how many daughters I'm going to have, how many years
they're going to be supported by it. If the property you bought
from me was at risk to being collected by them, you would
have no idea how much would be at risk. Okay, so in
that case, they can only collect directly from the estate, they cannot
collect from third parties. Okay, that's one example. Another example is that
I go ahead
and
I sell... and Michael here, we'll make me again the whatever, I
don't know. Michael goes ahead and he sells land to me, okay?
And I go ahead and I sell it to David, okay? Now,
David, there's an implicit or explicit clause that if it turns out
that unbeknownst to me that land was actually did not legally belong
to Michael and it was stolen land, and basically it's going to
be taken away from you because I never had the real title
to it, okay? There's an implicit clause that you can come and
get compensated from me, okay? So you have essentially a lien on
me for the cost of that land, okay? If that land winds
up having been stolen. But let's say since you bought that land,
you've built a condominium on it. That land is now worth a
million dollars, okay? And now it's seized from you, okay? So are
you going to... you now can tell me to pay up the
million dollars, okay? You have that right to even collect your investments
in that land from me. Okay, but let's say I have no
money. Let's say I've sold my land... other lands elsewhere. You want
to get paid back, you can't come to me, where are you
going to go? You're going to go to the people who have
purchased my land. How much when they purchase my land and they
know there's a risk to the land they purchased... the risk to
the land they purchased is you have a lien on my estate
for potentially being compensated for any land that you bought. Are you...
are we all sufficiently confused now? Okay. It's very confusing because anytime
you buy land, whenever I buy land from somebody, I get a
lien on that person's property in case that land winds up having
been stolen and I have a right to be
compensated, okay?
I like this... like there would be so many and... like okay,
the daughters, right? You provide them and then maybe I sold to
someone else but then I've got some debt that might come up
in the future...
title insurance. I know. It's... I can't figure it out. Every sale
of land, in the normal case, entails with it liens that are
created on the seller's land in case that sale went bad, okay?
So the point is those liens that you have on my land,
if that sale went bad, you can collect that amount from people
who I sold other land to up to the sale value. But
if you want to be compensated for improvements that you made on
that land, you can't collect from some third parties. Then they're accepting
unknown risk. Okay, so those are the cases. That second case was
a little more complicated. But basically, when the amount of the lien
is unknown and to be determined later, then they cannot collect from
third parties. Yes, Charlie?
Yeah, I mean it sounds weird, but we have that even in
this country today. You never can be absolutely sure that there aren't
any liens going to pop up, and that's why you get title
insurance.
Okay, there you go. All right, so and then it's just the
actuaries that have to figure out all the crazy possibilities. Okay, so
now it says like this: מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what is... why
is it that you cannot collect from third parties? I basically already
told you, but the גמרא's Gemara going to nuance it in two
ways in these scenarios. אמר עולא אמר ריש לקיש לפי שאין כתובים.
Amar Ulla Amar Reish Lakish, Lefi she'ein ketuvim. So they don't say
because the amount is not fixed, which is what the גמרא's Gemara
going to wind up saying, which I think is the simpler explanation.
It's going to say because the... because it's not written. Meaning people
don't know about this debt, okay? Now, we're going to find out,
the גמרא's Gemara going to say, "What do you mean they don't
know about this debt? How could they know about this debt less
than other things?" And then in the end, what it's really going
to wind up being is that the reason they don't know about
it is because the amount isn't fixed. Okay, but it's a slightly
different reason for the תקנה. takkana. Rather than saying it's unfair for
you, the purchaser, to incur debt when you don't know the amount,
when the amount could... you know, could... be very, very high, you
don't even know the risk you're assuming, we actually say because the
amount is indeterminate, people are unaware that they're even that they're even
assuming any risk about that. Okay? So it has more to do
with their ignorance that the debt exists rather than with the fact
that it's just not fair to assume undetermined debt. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this: משום דלא כתיבי. mishum delo kesivi.
מפני שאין כתובין. mipnei sheein kesuvin. אמר ליה רבי אבא לעולא, Amlei
Rabbi Abba leUlla, והא מזוני אשה ובנות כמאן דכתיבי דמו. veha Mezuni
Isha VeBanos dekman dechesivi dami. What are you talking about? First of
all, רש"י Rashi says in the case about about I'll pay you
back if the land winds up to be stolen and I'll pay
you back for any of your expenses, רש"י Rashi actually says actually
says רש"י Rashi that is written in the שטר. shtar. What do
you mean it's not written? So רש"י Rashi says, well, even though
it's written, nobody really knows about it or pays attention to it
because it's not determined. Okay, so it's really not about it being
written or not, it's really about its indeterminate nature means that people
aren't so aware of it. And now the גמרא Gemara does the
reverse. It says, wait a minute, the case about the fact that
I will my estate will support my wife and my daughters, so
even though that even though that's not written in the כתובה, kesuba,
חז"ל Chazal said that I have to do that, that's part of
my כתובה kesuba obligations and it has the weight as if it
were written. So that also is written. So the גמרא Gemara says:
ומזוני אשה ובנות דכמאן דכתיבי דמו, uMezuni Isha VeBanos dekman dechesivi dami,
that's as if it was written, וקתני אין מוציאין, uchtani ein motziin,
and nevertheless you can't collect from third parties. אמר ליה התם מעיקרא
הכי אתקין. Amlei hasam meikara hachi itkin. No, no, no, that was
the nature of the weight that חז"ל Chazal gave it. כתובין הן
אצל בני חורין, Kesuvin hein etzel bnei chorin, when my wife and
daughters come to collect from the actual estate itself, their debt has
the weight of as if it's written in a שטר. shtar. ואין
כתובין הן אצל משועבדים, Veein kesuvin hein etzel meshubadim, and when they
come to collect from third parties, it doesn't have that weight. Okay?
So basically we're saying these types of things are like because they're
a little fuzzy they don't have the it's they're not seen as
as being well known and we have to protect the purchasers, even
though some of them are written or do have a weight of
being written. אמר ליה רבי זירא לרבי אסי—so, Amlei Rabbi Zeira leRabbi
Assi והא מזוני אשה ובנות... veha Mezuni Isha VeBanos... I'm sorry, did
I skip a line? משועבדים. meshubadim. וכן אמר רבי אסי אמר רבי
יוחנן מפני שאין כתובין. Vechein amar Rabbi Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan mipnei
sheein kesuvin. אמר ליה רבי זירא לרבי אסי, Amlei Rabbi Zeira leRabbi
Assi, והא מזוני אשה ובנות כמאן דכתיבי דמו וקתני אין מוציאין? veha
Mezuni Isha VeBanos keman dechesivi dami uchtani ein motziin? What do you
mean it's not written? By the case of the wife and the
daughters it's as if it's written. אמר ליה מעיקרא הכי אתקין כתובין
הן אצל בני חורין ואין כתובין הן אצל משועבדים. Amlei meikara hachi
itkin kesuvin hein etzel bnei chorin veein kesuvin hein etzel meshubadim.
Okay,
so it's written vis-a-vis the estate, not vis-a-vis third parties. The basic
point is that the logic here, it all goes back to the
logic that we don't know the amount. But the point here is
because we don't know the amount, it's not it's unfair to subject
somebody to that risk, the point is because we don't know the
amount, the person isn't even aware that they're assuming the risk. Okay,
the risk nobody sort of talks about it when it's vague and
so on, so the person isn't even aware that there such a
risk is being assumed. So I don't know, רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina's
explanation is much easier. So we're going to focus on רבי חנינא.
Rabbi Chanina. That's what the גמרא Gemara focuses on anyway. רבי חנינא
אמר מפני שאין קצובים. Rabbi Chanina amar mipnei sheein ktzuvim. It's not
because people don't know about it, it's because it's not fixed. And
since it's not fixed, the it's unfair to assume that risk. Okay,
איבעיא להו, ibaya lehu, they asked a question: רבי חנינא קצובים וכתובין
בעי? Rabbi Chanina ktzuvim vekesuvim baei? For it for somebody to be
to be to
for third parties to be able to be collected from, does it
have to both be a fixed amount and written in the document?
או דלמא כתובין אף על פי שאין קצובים? o dilma kesuvim af
al pi sheein ktzuvim? Or what would be if it would be
a fixed amount that's not written in the document? Now רש"י Rashi
says what's a fixed amount that's not written in a document? So
רש"י Rashi says it's a מלוה על פה. milve al peh. It's
a loan without a document. I lend you a thousand dollars, that's
a fixed amount, it's not written. But תוספות Tosafos says that's clearly
wrong, we know that a מלוה על פה milve al peh does
not collect from does not have liens. But the question here is,
תוספות Tosafos says that might have specific issues to do with loans.
The question here is other types of debts that are incurred with
a when there's a fixed amount, okay, you could think about a
case let's say מזיק, mazik, there's no שטר shtar written but it's
you know but there's a fixed amount, it's not going to the
amount isn't going to go up. Other types of debts that are
incurred, right, without a document, not a loan where I could have
prepared a document and there's other reasons.
Meaning מזיק mazik מזיק טפילי, I mean but because of a person
you don't know how long they'll be sick...
Right, right, let's say מזיק property, other types of cases of loans
of debts that are incurred that aren't debts, okay, when the amount
is fixed but no שטר shtar has been drawn up.
Like a קנס? knas? Yeah, I mean we'll see some cases in
the גמרא. Gemara. Would he say that that would be a case
where I would have liens and could collect from a third party?
Is that enough that it's a fixed amount? Okay, תא שמע, ta
shema, come and hear. דאתמר: deitmar: מי שמת והניח שתי בנות. mi
shemeis vehiniach shtei banos. Somebody died and he left two daughters. Now
in addition to daughters getting supported by the estate until they get
married, they also have a prefixed dowry from the estate when they
do get married. And their dowry is a ten percent, okay, of
the estate. I mean whatever, we won't go into the specifics about
that but let's just call it that. Okay? So of course the
question is is it ten percent of what's left or ten percent
of the principal that's left, if a guy has eleven daughters is
the eleventh one out? Okay, anyway we're not going to worry about
that now. דאתמר: deitmar: מי שמת, mi shemeis, he died. והניח... vehiniach...
איתמר. Itmar. מי שמת, Mi shemeis, he died. והניח שתי בנות, Veheniyach
shtei banos, he leaves over two daughters. ובן, Veben, and a son.
Okay, so the son inherits the estate, the daughters have their right
to be supported and the dowry. וקדמה הראשונה, Vekadmah harishona, the first
one went ahead and got married, ונטלה עשור נכסים vnatla isur nechasim
and she took her 10th dowry, her 10th of the estate for
the dowry. ולא הספיקה שניה לגבות vlo hispika shniya ligbos and then
the second one didn't get her dowry yet because she's still single.
Okay, she's not married. עד שמת הבן ad shemeis haben and then
now the son died. Okay, so the son died. Who inherits the
estate now? If the son doesn't have any children? The sisters, right?
The daughters, they inherit the estate. So now this one, the second,
the younger one, let's say that she's younger, who isn't married yet,
she says great, now we split the estate, but you took 10%
off the top before we split it. I want my 10% off
the top before we split it. Okay. So in essentially, like, I
still have a lien on the estate, here's a way of thinking
about it. I have a right to 10%. I have a lien
on the estate. That was a debt owed me when Dad died.
Okay, I've got a lien on the estate. Okay, we're now splitting
the estate. So five, so the five- half of that, 5%, is
now the property you got. I'm going to, I'm going to exercise
my lien and take, you know, the other 5% back from you.
Alright? That's what she's saying. That seems like a reasonable claim. Okay.
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, שניה ויתרה, shniya vitra, the second
one loses out. ואמר רבי חנינא, ve'amar Rabbi Chanina, and Rabbi Chanina
got very upset. The same Rabbi Chanina who said that the issue
is ככתובים אף על פי שאין כתובים. kektuvim af al pi she'ein
ktuvim. This
by the way is an example of קצוב, katsov, it's a fixed
amount, 10%, but it's not written in any document. Okay, so that's
an example.
It's like כמאן דקצוב. kman d'katsov.
Yeah, okay, but the Gemara has- says now that it's not כמאן
דקצוב. kman d'katsov. So anyway, alright, so what did Rabbi Chanina say?
גדולה מזו אמרו. gdola mizo amru. He says, "What? The second one
loses out? There's even cases where she's entitled to even more, like
even a bigger case." What's a bigger case? מוציאין לפרנסה ואין מוציאין
למזונות. motzin l'parnasa ve'ein motzin l'mezonos. Okay,
this is called פרנסה, parnasa, this idea of the dowry is called
פרנסה. parnasa. So he said, let's say that the estate- that- that
there was property that was sold in Dad's life, okay, to other
parties. Okay. Can now the daughters collect with liens that party- property
in the hand of third parties? Can they collect that for their
dowry and for their מזונות? mezonos? So you already know the answer
for the מזונות. mezonos. Can they collect from third parties for their
מזונות? mezonos? What does our Mishna say?
The מזונות mezonos for the daughters, right, the ongoing support? Can they
collect from third parties? The Mishna says no, right, that's the- because
it's an indeterminate amount, that's the way the third parties are protected.
But Rabbi Chanina says that's only for the מזונות, mezonos, when they're
coming to- because that's not- determined amount. When they're coming to collect
their 10% dowry, they can collect from third parties, from property the
father- why it's crazy! Somebody who buys knows that there are pre-existing
liens on the estate.
No, but mean-
meaning- he doesn't know how many daughters the guy will have. What?
Right. Yeah, so that's a question. Would it be if the- maybe
it's only the- the- daughter, you know, based on the number of
daughters when it was purchased? I don't know, I have to think
about it. But it could be that that's the case. Anyway.
But at the time the transaction is made, the assets in the
estate could be different when he finally dies. Right. And so 10%
of that is different.
Oh, that's a good point too. Oh, that's a good point. So
when I bought it, I knew you had one daughter and I
knew the 10% was- you had $1000 to your name was 100
bucks, right? Now the guy dies, he has a million dollars, or
whatever. So 10% of that, even if he has no more daughters,
that's a good question. Oh, that's a good question.
Plus, his estate is much bigger than what he has at the
moment, right?
Yeah, but he- her debt is 10% of the estate when the
guy dies.
Right, but if he has a million dollar estate-
Yeah, but when I purchased the land from the guy, I only
knew I was incurring a 10% of a $10,000 estate.
Right, but now I'm realizing I'm confused about the guy- so someone
passes away, right, they have X amount to their name. Right. The
daughter is entitled to 10%. Yes. So at what point are you
going to need to go get it from some- if he's in
debt, then he doesn't have an-
Oh, I
see the point.
Oh, that's a good point. So why would you be מוציא motzi
if- I guess the point would be that the son inherits the
estate and then by the time it's time for the girls to
get- to get married, the son has gambled away all the money,
let's say. So you could have a case where what they were
entitled to wasn't around for them when it was time for them
to get married and then they have to go to third parties.
But it's a good question, right? I mean you'd have to have
that scenario. Anyway, so, okay. What? Yeah.
If-
if she gets that 10% lien on the property, and she has
two daughters- Yes.
Do they split it?
No, that's not the way it works. Each are entitled to 10%.
That's the הלכה. halacha. Okay.
What?
10% for one daughter, he had one daughter?
Yeah, but it would be 20% for two daughters. That's the way
it works.
Or 110% for eleven daughters.
Okay, so anyway, all right. Okay, so, all right, let's keep on
going. So it says, anyway, רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina says the daughter's
entitled to collect her עישור נכסים issur nechasim from third parties. That's
a fixed amount and she does have a lien. So therefore, if
she can collect it from a third party, she should certainly be
able to collect it from her sister. Okay? So he says והמוציא,
vekhamotzi,
okay, ואת אמרת שניה ויתרה? ve'at amarta shniya vitra?
You're telling me that she loses her 10% and she can't
collect
it from her sister? So that's the debate. But what we see
is that רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina says that she has a lien
and can collect from third parties, this עישור נכסים. issur nechasim. So
this is a perfect example and answer to our question. והפרנסה, veha
parnasa, this dowry, דמיקץ קייץ, demikat katz, a fixed amount, מכתב לא
כתיבן, michtav lo kvisan, and it's not written. והמוציאה, vekhamotzia, and she's
now collecting it from a third party. So you see that that's
what רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina says it works. So Michael, who's always,
you know, channeling the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא Gemara says, No, שאני
פרנסה כיון דאית ליה קלא כמאן דכתיבא דמי, shani parnasa keivan de'is
lei kala keman dechtiva dami, because everybody knows about this 10%. You
know, maybe again, maybe the amount, the support from the estate is
a vaguer amount, so people don't know about it, but this is
so well known that it's as if it's written. Of course, if
you say a fixed amount is so well known it's as if
it's written, it makes the whole question moot because every case that's
fixed is going to be like it's written. But let's see as
the גמרא Gemara continues. On the face of it, that was a
very good proof. Okay, מתיבי רב הונא בר מנוח. mative Rav Huna
bar Manoach.
It still, let me, it just begs the question, like, you know,
how do you engage in real estate transactions?
Yeah, I don't know, I don't know. Yeah, I know, it's crazy.
מתיבי רב הונא בר מנוח: mative Rav Huna bar Manoach: מתו בנותיהם,
mesu benoseihem, מתו, mesu, בנותיהם ניזונות מנכסים בני חורין, benoseihem nizonos minechasim
bnei chorin, והיא ניזונת מנכסים משועבדים. vehi nizonos minechasim meshu'abadim. Okay,
so you're going to love this case. Okay, which is the following.
A woman has a daughter. She gets married to another guy who's
now a stepfather to the daughter. This guy, she says, if you
want me to marry you, buddy,
you've got to make a commitment to pay, to support my daughter,
my daughter, your stepdaughter, which you don't have any legal obligation to.
You have to make a commitment to support her for the next
five years. So fine, he does that, he commits to support her
for the next five years. Presumably he doesn't have to put it
in writing. It can be part of the תנאים tnayim of the
marriage and so that's going to be a case of קייץ, katz,
it's a fixed amount, five years, and it's not written. Okay? Then
this guy goes ahead and, I don't know, divorces her. Okay? So
she now goes, but her daughter's still entitled, even now that she's
divorced, her daughter's still entitled to five years of support. Like, that's
independent of her being in an ongoing marriage. So the daughter's still
supported five years. She goes and she marries another guy. And she
says to the other guy, You want to marry me? You gotta
support my daughter for the next five years. So he agrees. So
during now, while this is happening, the daughter is getting supported for
five years from one of the guys, and from the other guy
she's getting the cash and she's banking it. Okay? So the daughter's
in a very nice position. Okay? Now, what happens? Yeah, you know
all that from...
you don't. That's all the background. That's not yet in any one
of the words. That was the context from which, the context from
which this was ripped. Okay?
Now, now, those two guys die. Okay? So this daughter who now
is, by the way, getting doubly supported, she actually has more right
than their natural daughters because she has a שטר shtar and, or
not a שטר, shtar, she has liens, right, that pre-existed and so
on. So let's see what happens now that those two guys die.
מתו, mesu, those guys die, בנותיהם, benoseiam, their own daughters, ניזונות מנכסים
בני חורין, nizonos minechasim bnei chorin, can only be supported from the
property that's actually in the estate, not held by third parties, because
that's what we know, daughters are supported by the property in the
estate. והיא, vehi, this daughter, who had a fixed amount, five years,
right, and from these two guys, they were only their stepdaughter, but
she's basically just like a בעלת חוב, ba'alas chov, she's like a
creditor, והיא ניזונת מנכסים משועבדים, vehi nizonos minechasim meshu'abadim, and she can
go ahead and collect her, what's owed to her even from third
parties, מפני שהיא כבעלת חוב. mipnei shehi keba'alas chov.
Okay, so you got that scenario? Now, the point is, we're assuming
that this five-year commitment was verbal and not written. Why, I don't
know. I mean, you would think he would need to write it,
or the wife would certainly want proof. But anyway, it's going to
be evidence that קייץ ולא כתיבי katz velo ksivi is entitled to
get even from third parties. So the גמרא Gemara says, so isn't
that another proof like רבי חנינא? Rabbi Chanina? הכא במאי עסקינן בשקנו
מידו. hacha bemai askinan beshekinnu miyado. Oh, they actually did not just
do it verbally, one wonders how it would have been binding if
it was just verbal. They actually did a קנין, kinyan, they did
like a חליפין, chalipin, they did like a סודר. sudar. And since
you do a חליפין, chalipin, that creates a sense of a debt
that you don't know, that that... is so strong it even could
collect from third parties, it even, you know, even more than normal
circumstances. So that's why. So the גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי בנות
נמי בשקנו. Ee hachi banos nami b'shekonu. אי הכי בנות נמי. Ee
hachi banos nami.
So if we're talking about, you know, the whole point was to
contrast the stepdaughter to the daughters. If you're going to say the
stepdaughter's a special case that they did a קנין, kinyan, so the
daughters should also be the case that they did a קנין. kinyan.
And if that's true, then everybody should be entitled to collect from
third parties. That's the strength of a קנין. kinyan. So the גמרא
Gemara says, no. בשקנו לזו ולא קנו לזו. B'shekonu l'zo v'lo konyu
l'zo. No, no, no, you only did a קנין kinyan for the
stepdaughter, not for his daughters. And that's why she has more strength
and that's why she can collect from third parties. The גמרא Gemara
says מאי פסיקא, mai pseeka, so why are we making a difference,
meaning
right, the point of the ברייתא braita was to tell you that
the stepdaughter has more rights than the daughter. So how why should
we be reading into it that there was a special case you
did a קנין kinyan for one and not the other? That doesn't,
right, the פשט pshat seems to be fundamentally to tell you the
stepdaughter has more rights than the daughter in this case. So the
גמרא Gemara says מאי פסיקא, mai pseeka, so the גמרא Gemara says
no. בת אשתו דהויא בשעת קנין מהני לה קנין. Bas ishto dehavya
b'sha'as kinyan mahni lah kinyan.
No, no, no, here's why. Yes, he did a קנין kinyan in
both cases. But his stepdaughter, when he did the קנין, kinyan, the
stepdaughter was around, so that was binding and that gave her liens,
and those liens entitled her to even in the hand of a
third party. בתו דלא הויא בשעת קנין, Beeto d'lo havya b'sha'as kinyan,
his daughter that didn't exist when he got married to his wife
even if he committed to his wife to support her through a
קנין, kinyan, he didn't really even have to, it was a rabbinic
obligation, ולא מהני לה קנין, v'lo mahni lah kinyan, it wouldn't help.
Okay, so basically it's saying fundamentally the only reason by the stepdaughter
she can collect from third parties is that there was a קנין
kinyan done, חליפין chalipin done and so on, and even if he
would have done that by his daughters it wouldn't have given them
any extra strength because they weren't around at that time.
And we're saying
this, what, yes, this is קצוב katzuv for the five years, not
the daughters.
But I mean the amount, meaning I understand five years is a
determined time but the amount?
Presumably, presumably there's a standard amount of support. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says, now the גמרא Gemara is going to have a case
where his daughter is around at the time he gets married. How
is his daughter around at the time he gets married other than
he had sex outside of marriage? So the גמרא Gemara says, מי
והיכא, mi veheicha, so the גמרא Gemara says one minute, I can
give you a case where his daughters were around at the time
of marriage. מי לא עסקינן, Mi lo askinan, who says we're not
talking about a case דהוו תרוייהו בשעת קנין, dehavu tarye b'sha'as kinyan,
that you can even have the daughters when he was obligating himself
to his wife. His own daughters? How? והיכי דמי, Veheichi dami, what's
the case? דגירשה ואהדרה. D'girshah v'hadrah. He divorced his wife and remarried
her. So now at the second remarrying he's obligated to his daughters
and his daughters are already around, so for the special case of
קנין kinyan then the daughters should also be entitled to collect from
third parties. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא, ella, okay. So finally
the answer which to me seemed pretty obvious from the beginning. בתו
דבתנאי בית דין קאכלה לא מהני לה קנין. Beeto d'bitnai beis din
ka'achlah lo mahni lah kinyan.
His daughter, she is entitled to be supported by the estate because
חז"ל Chazal entitled her. That's a natural obligation of the כתובה. kesubah.
So the קנין kinyan there is completely superfluous. So even if you
did a קנין, kinyan, it doesn't give her any extra rights. So
her fundamental rights are כתובה kesubah rights, those are limited to the
estate property, not to property in the hands of third parties. A
קנין kinyan is superfluous, she already has those that right and therefore
she doesn't get extra rights even with a
קנין. kinyan. בת אשתו דלאו בתנאי בית דין קאכלה, Bas ishto d'lav
bitnai beis din ka'achlah, his stepdaughter, she had no rights if he
didn't obligate himself. She would have no rights. In that
case, so מהני לה קנין, mahni lah kinyan, when he goes ahead
and does a קנין, kinyan, that gives her the right and even
for third parties. But the גמרא Gemara is not happy. וכי מיגרע
גרע? V'chi migra gara? גמרא Gemara says I don't get it, even
though the daughter came in with more rights, okay, so just because
she started better off, she came in with more rights, why when
he actually does the קנין kinyan should that not entitle her to
even more, right? Why shouldn't the קנין kinyan upgrade her and give
her the right to collect from third parties? You still haven't answered
it. אלא, Ella, here, we'll try this way. בתו כיון דבתנאי בית
דין קאכלה אימא צררי אתפסה. Beeto keivan d'bitnai beis din ka'achlah eima
tzorari asfasa. The last thing the גמרא Gemara says is fine, but
because his obligation to his daughter is so fundamental and it starts
from an obligation of בית דין, beis din, even if he did
a קנין kinyan and even if in principle he gave her rights
to collect from third parties, the בית דין beis din won't let
her collect from third parties. Why not? It's a little ironic. Why
not? Because the בית דין beis din will say listen, since your
father had such a fundamental obligation to you, okay, we are concerned
that he might have already even prepaid his debt to you and
put it in some escrow account and therefore we're not going to
let you collect from third parties. So that's a very complicated, what?
Even if there's no escrow account, even if we don't know about
it, I don't know if you know that there isn't but we
don't know about it. So it's very very complicated. But obviously the
simple sense of this once again is that when it's a fixed
amount without being written that you are entitled to collect from third
parties, but in order to get out of it the גמרא Gemara
made a very convoluted explanation that there was a קנין חליפין kinyan
chalipin here and that's what made it like it was written and
that's why. as a special case, but normally you could not collect
from third parties. I have to tell you, I didn't understand this
גמרא Gemara at all because to me the simplest answer is, not
because I didn't understand what it was saying, I saw that, I
understood what it was saying, but I didn't understand it because, because,
no, because like I don't understand if I'm agreeing to support my
stepdaughter, right, I don't understand how I can verbally obligate myself. Like,
like what creates that obligation? I would think to create the obligation
I need to do a קנין. kinyan. So of course we're talking
about that I did a קנין. kinyan. How else did I obligate
myself to my stepdaughter? It doesn't come through my words, whereas the
case by my daughters, that obligation is automatic with a כתובה. kesubah.
So that would have been the easiest explanation of the גמרא. Gemara.
Yes, you know why we're talking about that he did a קנין
kinyan with his stepdaughter and not with his daughters? Because he needs
to do it with his daughters and he needed to do it
with his, I don't get it. But anyway, the simple sense of
this is that כתובים kesubim even if it's not written down has
a lien and that's the case of the stepdaughter, but maybe the
case of the stepdaughter was a special case that there was a
קנין kinyan involved. Yes.
That case where we're concerning מרי טעינם, mari teidim, couldn't she collect
with a שבועה?
shevuah? Yeah, it's a good question. תוספות Tosafot asks that. Okay.
And isn't מוציאין לפרנסה motzin leparnasah agreed upon by everybody?
Well, yeah, that's also the same. Like where we're saying that this
is a רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina case and now it seems to
be actually that it's a... but רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina actually was
the one who challenged רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan by מוציאין לפרנסה motzin
leparnasah so it was consistent. Okay, תא שמע, ta shma, so we're
still going to try to prove this. כתובים אף על פי שאין
כתובים. kesubim af al pi she'ein kesubim. אמר רבי נתן, Amar Rabbi
Natan, אימתי? eimasai? בזמן שקדם מקח שני לשבחו של ראשון. bizman shekodam
mekach sheni lishvacho shel rishon. So, when is it that David there
that now improves the property he bought from me that is going
to wind up to have been stolen and he made a million
dollars of capital improvements on it? And now he wants to collect,
and he wants to collect from Michael who bought, you know, who
bought property from me, Michael has the property he wants to collect.
And we tell you David, you cannot collect from the improvements, you
can only collect from the purchase amount. So this ברייתא baraita qualifies
and says one minute, אימתי, eimasai, when is that true? בזמן
שקדם מקח שני לשבחו של ראשון,
bizman shekodam
mekach sheni lishvacho shel rishon, when Michael here bought the property from
me before you made your improvements, because then he didn't know how
much those improvements were going to be, right? Right? אבל קדם שבחו
של ראשון למקח שני, aval kodam shevacho shel rishon lemekach sheni, if
you made your capital improvements and then he bought the property and
you knew that he had a right to collect any compensation from
me if that property was stolen, you knew what you were getting
yourself into, right? If your improvements had already been made. In that
case, גובה מנכסים משועבדים, goveh minechasim hameshuhbadim, you can collect from Michael.
Okay, that's a pretty... makes a lot of sense, right? Because then
the amount is determined. So תוספות Tosafot says that what this גמרא
Gemara is doing is this גמרא Gemara is basically coming to support
רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina and to say it's not about the amount
not being written. Here's a perfect case where it wasn't written, but
once the amount was known, you're entitled to collect, right? Is that
clear? So you see the issue is not that it wasn't written.
The issue is that it wasn't fixed. And once, once Michael knew
the risk he was assuming, David is entitled to collect. עלמא משום
דלא קציב הוה. alma mishum d'lo katziv hava. Ah, you see that
the problem is because, you know,
because the improvements didn't happen before the debt, meaning you see that
the issue the way תוספות Tosafot reads this is, I mean before
the purchase. You see that the issue is the indeterminate amount. You
see that רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina is right. So the גמרא Gemara
says תנאי היא. tannai hi. Fine, this debate, is it because they're
written or is it because it's a fixed amount, is a debate
of תנאים. tannaim. דתניא בברייתא, detanya b'baraita, אין מוציאין לאכילת פירות ולא
לשבח קרקעות ולא למזון האשה
והבנות מנכסים משועבדים מפני תיקון העולם. ein motzin l'achilat peirot velo lishvach
karkaot velo limzon ha'ishah vehabanot min hanechasim hameshuhbadim mipnei tikkun ha'olam.
Because of תיקון העולם. tikkun ha'olam. What's the תיקון העולם? tikkun ha'olam?
לפי שאין כתובים, lefi she'ein kesubim,
because the amount is not written. So here a ברייתא baraita explicitly
identifies the problem that the amount is not written and therefore the
people who purchase the property don't know about it. And אמר רבי
יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yosei, so רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei pushes back and
he says וכי מה תיקון העולם יש בזה? vechi mah tikkun ha'olam
yesh bazeh? What type of תיקון העולם tikkun ha'olam is it? Meaning
not like I don't understand why you're coming to protect the purchasers,
but like it's not about that. It's not about the fact that
it's not written. You don't need to do a תיקון העולם tikkun
ha'olam if it's not written. Presumably, like we said before, if it's
a fixed amount even if it's not written, you need to be
aware of these things. Okay, so it has nothing to do with
it not being written. הלא אין קצוב, halo ein katzuv, the issue
is that it's an indeterminate amount and they're assuming an unknown risk.
Okay, so by the end, the גמרא Gemara basically seems to say
that it is about being fixed. If it's fixed and not written,
then you do have liens. The issue is really like a either-or:
one has to do completely with the fact that it's not written,
okay, and that's what it's about, and the other has to do
completely with the fact that it's not fixed. But if it's known
and fixed, then you do have liens, and that would be the
case that David made the capital improvements and afterwards Michael bought the
property. In that case when it was fixed, David is entitled to
collect from those...
meaning from other property of yours.
Right, other property, exactly.
So I'm just to know that David bought another one of your
properties.
Yeah, you can do a title search and find out which of
my properties I sold. And then
know... That's true. Okay.
Moving on. Yes. I gotta tell you, I like the fourth פרק
תיקון עולם perek Tikun Olam more than this פרק
תיקון עולם.
perek Tikun
Olam.
Yes, and then improvements that are integral to the property, improvements that
are like if you build a
condo is not really improving the property.
But really, would they then share, could in other words, even if
he lost the property, stays still on the condominium.
Yeah, I don't know. It's a good question. It's a good question.
Okay, when we get to בבא מציעא Bava Metzia or the other
סוגיות sugyas that deal with that, I'll get my head in there.
Okay, המוצא מציאה. HaMotzi Metzia. Now,
this is easier, okay, and a little bit more intuitive also. I
go and I return a lost object to you and I say,
here's your wallet, and you say, but there's only 20 bucks in
here, and I said, yeah, I know, that's what I found, and
says, no, there was 200 bucks. Okay. So why isn't that like
a, like a מודה במקצת? Modeh B'miktzat? Okay, I admit that there
was that 20 bucks of this is yours, you saying that there
was 200, and I should have to take a שבועה, shvua, okay,
or something. So the answer is like, wait one minute, we gotta
protect this, nobody's gonna return a lost object if they're gonna just
get in trouble because somebody's gonna claim that it was more. Okay.
So I remember once when I was growing up I was reading,
remember in the, I mean they still have that paper, I just
don't, haven't read it for decades, the Jewish Press, but they have
all these like מעשה'לעך maisehlach and stories or whatever. Anyways, you know,
so there was this one where there was about something like this
that a guy came to return the thing and the guy said
there was 200 rubles in here and he said, no, it was
empty, whatever. Anyway, so they asked the rabbi, so the rabbi said,
so wait minute let me get this straight, you say there was
200 rubles and he returned something that didn't have 200 rubles, so
says, oh, must be it was a different, it wasn't the same
object, so must be not your wallet. So anyways, that's one way
of solving it.
So anyway, alright, but anyway, but that's the principle. So the המוצא
מציאה, Motzi Metzia, the guy who finds lost object, doesn't have to
take a שבועה shvua מפני תיקון עולם. mipnei tikun olam. אמר רב
יצחק, Amar Rav Yitzchak, now רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak is going to
make a ruling that seems to completely ignore this, or I shouldn't
say seems, does completely ignore this. אמר רב יצחק, Amar Rav Yitzchak,
שני כיסים קשורים מצאת לי, shnei kisim kshurim matzata li, I say
to you, you found two wallets tied up in a bundle, והלה
אומר לא מצאתי אלא אחד. v'halah omer lo matzati ela echad.
Wait, you're going to me and saying what I found?
Yeah, like I see you, I see you picked it up on
the street or something like that. Hey, you just found, or I
heard, maybe I heard. I heard you found my wallets, they were
two of them that were combined, that were tied up, והלה אומר,
v'halah omer, and you say, לא מצאתי אלא אחד, lo matzati ela
echad, no, no, no, there was only one of them. נשבע, Nishba,
you have to make a שבועה, shvua, it's מודה במקצת, modeh b'miktzas,
I claim two and you admitted one. שני שוורים קשורים מצאת לי,
Shnei shvarim kshurim matzata li, hey, I heard that you found two
of my oxen bound together, והלה אומר לא היה אלא אחד, v'halah
omer lo haya ela echad, there was only one, אינו נשבע. eino
nishba. You don't have to make a שבועה. shvua. Now, what's the
difference? מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? שוורים מנתחי הדדי, shvarim mitchini hadadi, because
oxen, even if they're bound together, will separate. So therefore when I
say you have two of my oxen, it's a טענת שמא, tainas
shema, because I really don't know you have two of my oxen,
even if I know you found the oxen, you know, something or
whatever, right, I somehow, I can't be sure that you found them
together, okay, whereas in the other case it's seen as a טענת
ברי, tainas bari, that if I know that you found my one
of them, my wallets, I know you found them both. Alright, that's
presumably the logic.
כיסים לא מנתחי הדדי, Kisim lo mitchini hadadi, but wallets don't naturally
just separate from one another. If you found one, you found the
other. Now, שני שוורים קשורים מצאת, והלה אומר מצאתי והחזרתי לך אחד
מהם, Shnei shvarim kshurim matzata v'halah omer matzati v'hechzarti lecha echad meihem,
some have a תניא נמי הכי, tanya nami hacha, it's a ברייתא,
braisa, some have a continuation of the statement. שני שוורים קשורים מצאת
shnei shvarim kshurim matzata, והלה אומר מצאתי והחזרתי לך אחד מהם, v'halah
omer matzati v'hechzarti lecha echad meihem, so this is a variation of
it. You found two oxen and he says, yes, I did find
two and I've already given you back one and here's the other
one. And I say, no, you didn't give me back any yet.
הרי זה נשבע, Harei zeh nishba, you have to take a שבועה.
shvua. Okay.
So basically, what we have here is, is a complete ignoring, other
than the case of the oxen which is a special case, a
complete ignoring of the principle that a המוצא מציאה motzi metzia doesn't
have to make a שבועה. shvua. Because here you are, you're a
good guy, you found an object, you're returning it or whatever, and
you have to make a שבועה shvua that it wasn't what I'm
claiming it was. So the גמרא Gemara says, לרב יצחק לית ליה
המוצא מציאה לא ישבע מפני תיקון עולם? L'Rav Yitzchak leis lei HaMotzi
Metzia lo yishava mipnei tikun olam? Did he not read our משנה?
Mishnah? So the גמרא Gemara says, no. הוא דאמר כרבי אליעזר בן
יעקב, Hu d'amar k'Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov, he's like רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov. There actually is an opinion that a
המוצא מציאה motzi metzia does have to take a שבועה, shvua, and
he's following that.
מחלוקת תנאים. Machlokes tannaim.
Yeah, that's the opinion of רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov, exactly. It's a מחלוקת תנאים, machlokes tannaim, דתניא, d'tanya, דתנא ברייתא.
d'tana braisa. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר פעמים שאדם
נשבע על טענת עצמו. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer pe'amim she'adam nishba
al ta'anat atzmo.
Sometimes a person will have to take a שבועה shvua on their
own claim, meaning, meaning they weren't even being challenged by the other
side, they were just being a good guy and coming forward and
they're going to have to take a שבועה, shvua, which is exactly
the המוצא מציאה motzi metzia case. You were a good guy, you
came forward, and now we're making you take a שבועה. shvua. Okay.
So what's the case? כיצד? Keitzad? מנה לאביך בידי, maneh l'avicha b'yadi,
I go to a guy and I say, your father borrowed a
hundred dollars from me, and he said, huh, what, like I don't
know about that. Okay, I came forth, but then I... And then
I say ואכלתי פרט, v'achalti prat, but I have to tell you
I was next to, not $100, I missed it. He, he gave
me $100 to watch of his, okay, and but I spent half
of it so basically here you know
I owe you $50, okay. והרי זה נשבע. v'harei zeh nishba. Okay,
so now you have to take a שבועה shvua because basically what
you're saying is it's like you're admitting that there was a hundred
dollar debt, you're left with fifty dollars to the debt, so you're
like a מודה במקצת. modeh b'miktzat. But you did it all to
yourself, right? You see? You got it? You basically said, like, you
know, I owed your father a hundred dollars and I paid back
fifty and I owe you the remaining fifty. So he says, okay,
make a שבועה shvua that you didn't really pay, that you paid
back fifty, maybe you didn't pay back any. But I'm the one
who came and admitted it to you. Okay, no, doesn't matter, מודה
במקצת. modeh b'miktzat. It seems completely crazy. Now the other question that
people will, would ask is and the גמרא's Gemara going to get
to it, but you know, even if you never learned the סוגיא
sugya of מיגו, migo, something in you should be rebelling and saying
I don't get it. I could have just kept quiet and said
nothing and I wouldn't pay you anything, so don't I have that,
you know, assumption that that entitles me to be believed when I'm
coming forth and saying I owe you fifty?
So that's the principle of like, alright, well we'll get to that,
but that's basically the principle of like מיגו migo or מיגו דאי
בעי שתיק, migo d'i baei shatik, which is even a stronger מיגו.
migo. I could have just kept quiet. So we'll see about this.
Okay, so,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
והרי זה נשבע, v'harei zeh nishba, וזהו שנשבע בתקנת עצמו. v'zehu she'nishba
b'takanat atzmo. And this is somebody
that you know that is making a שבועה shvua for on itself.
I think by the way I misexplained ואכלתי פרט, v'achalti prat, it
talks about that I returned half of it. I borrowed a hundred
and I returned half of it. Okay, וחכמים אומרים, v'Chachamim omrim, the
חכמים Chachamim say, אינו אלא כמשיב אבידה ופטור. eino ela k'meishiv aveida
u'patur. No, the
guy is doing צדקה, tzedakah,
you're giving back stuff that he didn't even know about, so you
don't have to take a שבועה shvua on the other half. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: So there you see
רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says that you know
that is not concerned with your good intentions and you still have
to do half. But the גמרא's Gemara got another problem. רבי אלעזר
בן יעקב לית ליה משיב אבידה פטור? Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov leit
lei meishiv aveida patur? Now this question is not the way תוספות
Tosafot explains the other question. Didn't he read our משנה? Mishna? We
already said he doesn't agree with our משנה. Mishna. But this question
is the following: forget our משנה, Mishna, forget תיקון עולם, tikkun olam,
okay, he should have a מיגו. migo. מיגו Migo I could have
said nothing. So forget תיקון עולם, tikkun olam, okay, which you could
have asked, why do you need a תיקון עולם? tikkun olam? Every
משיב אבידה meishiv aveida has a מיגו. migo. I didn't have to
tell you I found the object. Okay, but that's אי הכי נמי.
ei hachi nami. But basically the point is, put aside תיקון עולם
tikkun olam is the way תוספות Tosafot reads this. Why in רבי
אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov fine, let's say not everybody
agrees to the תיקון עולם. tikkun olam. But what happened to the
idea of a מיגו? migo? He could have just been quiet and
not done anything. Why is he, why does he still have to
take a שבועה? shvua? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר
רב בטענת קטן. amar Rav b'taanat katan. Okay, so he didn't really
just admit it on his own. The,
the guy who he's giving back the money to, the, the person
you know who he's talking about his father's he owes money to
his father, he's talking to a kid. The kid is saying, hey,
you owed me money. So the גמרא Gemara says well, if he's
a קטן, katan, הלכתית halachically it's not a טענה, taana, but you
don't have the claim like I could have been quiet, because this
11-year-old was bringing me in and yelling and screaming that I owed
his father money. So it's not just, oh, I could have said
nothing. Legally it's not a טענה, taana, so that's what it means
טענת עצמו. taanat atzmo. There wasn't a legal claim against me, but
on the other hand I can't just say hey, I could have
said nothing, I was being pressured, the kid was yelling at me.
So that's how the גמרא's Gemara trying to answer. Well, at least
psychologically. I psychologically I can't say I would have been quiet if
this guy is yelling and screaming that I'm stealing money from him.
I had to say something. Yes. Ah yes,
but that could be, but let's not even go there, that's a
whole other level of complexity. So the גמרא Gemara says, בטענת קטן.
קטן מידי ממשא אית ביה? b'taanat katan. katan midi mamasha it beih?
One minute. There's no הלכתי halachic meaning to a challenge of a
קטן, katan, maybe even it wouldn't affect the מיגו, migo, a קטן
katan is ignored. דתנן אין נשבעין על טענת חרש שוטה וקטן. d'tnan
ein nishvain al taanat cheresh shoteh v'katan. That you don't make a
שבועה, shvua, so that shouldn't affect anything. So the גמרא Gemara says,
although I tried to the explanation I gave was pretty good for
that anyway, the גמרא Gemara says: מאי קטן? mai katan? פיין, fine,
גדול. gadol. Gotta love the גמרא. Gemara. מאי קטן? גדול. mai katan
gadol. Okay, so. So it's like a גמרא Gemara that says you
know, תנא אפילו כל שהוא, tanna afilu kol shehu, and then the
גמרא Gemara says כמה כל שהוא? kama kol shehu? Anyway, מאי קטן
mai katan? גדול. gadol. Okay fine, we don't literally mean a קטן.
katan. It is an adult. So ואמאי קרו ליה קטן? v'amai karu
lei katan? Why are you calling him קטן? katan? דלגבי מילי דאבוה
קטן הוא. d'lgabei milei d'avuh katan hu. Because he's ignorant of his
father's dealings, so he's like a minor. So therefore it's a case
where his טענה taana is a טענה taana in בית דין, Beis
Din, it had to be responded to. I can't say I could
have kept quiet, I don't have a מיגו, migo, but on the
other hand since he's really ignorant. I could've done, I could've denied
everything, so maybe that's why the חכמים *Chachamim* call it משיב אבידה
*meshiv aveidah* because I could've denied everything and רבי אליעזר בן יעקב
*Rebbi Eliezer ben Yaakov* says, no, in that case, you're מודה במקצת
*modeh b'miktzas* and you have to pay. Okay, so it's a type
of a case where on the one hand, you can't just say
it would've been easy to keep quiet, there was a טענה *ta'ana*,
but the guy on the other hand, the guy didn't know and
therefore חכמים *Chachamim* call you a משיב אבידה *meshiv aveidah* and רבי
אליעזר בן יעקב *Rebbi Eliezer ben Yaakov* says, nope, in that case,
you have to pay that you're מודה במקצת *modeh b'miktzas*. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says, let's just read one more line, אי הכי *ee
hachi* the גמרא *Gemara* says טענת עצמו טענת אחרים הוא *ta'anas atzmo
ta'anas acherim hu*. It's not, therefore, what's the phrase when רבי אליעזר
בן יעקב *Rebbi Eliezer ben Yaakov* says you're going to pay on
your own, on your claim against yourself. This isn't your claim against
yourself. This is the other side making a claim against you. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says, okay, no, what we mean is טענת אחרים
והודאת עצמו *ta'anas acherim vehoda'as atzmo*. No, no, means fine, the other
side is making the claim, but you're admitting. So that's why he
calls it your, it's your own claim. גמרא *Gemara* says what are
you talking about? כולהו טענתא נמי טענת אחרים והודאת עצמו נינהו *kullehu
ta'anata nami ta'anas acherim vehoda'as atzmo ninhu*. So that's every case in
court. Every מודה במקצת *modeh b'miktzas*, this guy is making a claim
against me and I'm admitting half. Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* still
doesn't get, right, why is it that what is the case that
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב *Rebbi Eliezer ben Yaakov* says you're admitting half
and you have to go ahead and make a שבועה *shvua*, even
though, right, you could ממה נפשך *miman nafshach*, either the other side
is making a real claim against you and then we don't know
why you're calling it טענת עצמו *ta'anas atzmo*, we don't know why
the חכמים *Chachamim* say you're פטור *patur*. Or the other side, like
it sounds like, is making no claim against you and no real
claim against you and then we don't understand why רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב *Rebbi Eliezer ben Yaakov* says you're חייב *chayav* because you could've
just totally remained silent. So we're going to return tomorrow to figure
out what רבי אליעזר בן יעקב *Rebbi Eliezer ben Yaakov* and the
חכמים *Chachamim* are debating about this case of admitting half to somebody
about a debt to a father, what that debate would be about,
why one side says you'd be חייב *chayav* and the other side
says you'd be exempt.